Egmont Arens Papers
Egmont Arens Papers
1880-1966
Arens, Egmont, 1889-1966.
45 linear feet
Papers of the American industrial designer. Collection includes correspondence, research material, manuscripts, photographs, and sketches, reflecting Arens' career in industrial design. Clients include Columbian Rope Co., the Great Atlantic and Pacific Tea Co. (A&P), J.C. Penney, Philip Morris, and Reynolds Metals Co. Materials on the Flying Stag Press include correspondence with Rex Stout (1924-1936) and Rockwell Kent (1924-1933).
148817
Biographical History
Egmont Hegel Arens, industrial designer, was born in Cleveland, Ohio, on 15 December 1889, the son of Franz Xavier and Emma (Huegal?) Arens. He was a leading design pioneer in the fields of packaging and plastics and is credited with introducing "appetite appeal" in packaging design. From 1911 to 1914 he attended the University of New Mexico and in 1915-1916 the University of Chicago. Before beginning his career in design, he was a sports editor for the Albuquerque (N.M.) Tribune-Citizen, a bookseller in his own Washington Square Bookstore in New York's Greenwich Village (1917-1923), a salesman of fine printing produced by his own Flying Stag Press (1918-1927), and editor for the periodicals Vanity Fair (1922-1923) and Creative Arts (1925-1927), and the printer, publisher, and editor (1919-1925) of the artistic and literary periodical Playboy, which published works by D.D. Lawrence and Max Weber, among others.
In 1929 he entered the field of industrial design as the founder and director of the division of industrial styling at Calkins and Holden, and in 1935 he established his own New York design office. As an industrial designer his activities included product design, plastics research, product development, color consultation, office and industrial interior design, store planning, and package and trademark design. He designed business machines, electrical appliances, radios, furniture, toys, and boats for such diverse clients as Reynolds Metals, Philip Morris, A & P, and the Columbian Rope Company.
Egmont Arens was manager (1917-1920) and director (1920) of the Peoples Symphony Concerts in New York, which had been founded by his father. Besides serving as president (1929) of the American Union of Decorative Artists and Craftsmen, he was a member (1946) of the planning committee for the Center for Graphic Industries of New York University, president (1949-1950) of the Society of Industrial Designers, a member (1952) of the advisory committee of Pratt Institute, and a member of the United States delegation to the International Trade Fair, held in Liege, Belgium, in 1955. He was the co-author with Roy Sheldon of the 1935 book Consumer Engineering. From 1962 until his death he held the position of chairman of the board of Egmont Arens - DeRaffel, Inc. in New York. Egmont Arens died in New York City on 2 October 1966.
Scope and Contents of the Collection
The Egmont Arens Papers contain personal and business correspondence; business records; legal and financial records; organization records; original art, including layouts, plans and sketches; photographs and slides; published material, including books, clippings, labels, periodicals and reprints; and writings. The inclusive dates of these papers are 1883-1966; the bulk dates are 1930-1960.
The material is arranged under six major headings: Personal Correspondence, Industrial Design Records, Miscellany, Organization Records, Publication Records, and Writings. Material within each group is arranged either alphabetically or chronologically, as is material within subdivisions.
Personal Correspondence (1883-1966) contains the incoming and outgoing personal letters of Egmont Arens. There is also personal correspondence of members of Arens' family and his friends, among them Camille Davied Arens, Emma Huegal Arens, Josephine Bell Arens, Mathilde Zwilling Arens, Winifred B. Arens, Patricia Arens Cumming, and Margaret Laubenstein. Correspondence is arranged chronologically to the month. Undated correspondence is arranged alphabetically by the writer's name and is boxed immediately after the dated correspondence. Other correspondence is located elsewhere in these papers, especially in the industrial design section and boxes 29-30.
Industrial Design Records (1929-1966) contain materials relating to Arens' career as an industrial designer. The material is arranged in six subgroups:
The Client and Project File contains material generated by Arens in designing products of packaging on his own or for clients. Types of material include blueprints, clippings, correspondence, holograph notes, labels, layouts, news releases, patent applications and assignments, photographs, reports, and sketches. Of special interest is the folder "Diagram for Tomorrow" under Book Ideas which contains correspondence with Albert Einstein. Materials are arranged alphabetically by the name of the client or project and, within that are further subdivided by subject and type of document.
General Correspondence includes miscellaneous incoming and outgoing business letters which were originally located throughout the various files of the industrial design records. This correspondence is arranged chronologically.
The Office File contains materials relating to the operation of Arens' own design firms. Materials in this small file are arranged alphabetically by type.
Photographs and Slides are divided into three groups: Prints and Negatives, 35mm Slides, Lantern Slides. Prints and negatives are arranged alphabetically by names of client or subjects. Where there is more than one folder of photographs or negatives for a client, these are arranged alphabetically by subject. Thirty-five millimeter slides are divided into two groups according to the manner in which they were received: loose and boxed. Both groups are arranged alphabetically by subject. Because one box may contain slides of more than one subject, box and section numbers are indicated for each subject. The lantern slides, used by Arens to illustrate his lectures, are arranged alphabetically by his own general topic designations.
The Publicity File contains materials relating to the promotion of Arens' services as an industrial designer. This material is arranged alphabetically by type.
Writings contains writings in the field of industrial design, the greater portion by Arens himself. Materials are arranged alphabetically by author's name, then alphabetically by type. Articles, books and book reviews are arranged chronologically. Arens' lecture material is further subdivided by type. The manuscripts and correspondence section is arranged chronologically with undated articles arranged alphabetically at the end of that section. Notes and slide captions and background materials are arranged alphabetically by subject.
Miscellany (1901-1965) includes a melange of materials generated by the following people in addition to Egmont Arens: Camille Davied Arens, Emma Huegal Arens, Franz Xavier Arens, Josephine Bell Arens, Mathilde Zwilling Arens, Ralph Waldo Arens, Ruth Chrisman Arens, Patricia Arens Cumming, and J. Marie Egts.
Material is arranged alphabetically by individuals' last names, thereafter alphabetically by type of material or subject matter. Included are memorabilia, legal and financial records, diaries, photographs and negatives, medical records and a few pieces of correspondence. Titles of photographs and negatives in quotation marks on the shelf list are those given by Arens.
Organization Records (1936-1965) contains materials arising from Arens' membership in various organizations. It includes reports, minutes, membership lists, correspondence, and other similar material.
Publication Records (1918-1960) contains materials generated by Arens during his magazine editorial work and during the operation of his own Flying Stag Press. The material is arranged alphabetically by publishing house. Within the subsections on each publishing house, material is arranged alphabetically by type, and thereafter by author and/or title.
Writing (1915-1927) contains works by Arens and others on subjects other than industrial design. The material is arranged alphabetically by authors' names, thereunder by the type of work, and by the title.
Arrangement of the Collection
See Scope and Content, above.
Separated Material
The following items were removed from the collection and transferred to Rare Books for separate cataloging:
Brodsky, Horace, A Portfolio of Linoleum Cuts, New York, No. 6 of 100, signed by the artist 1920, 1920
Casanova, Giovanni Jacopo, Memoirs, 12 volumes, New York: Aventuros 1925
Cronyn, George, Sandbar Queen. Flying Stag Plays, No. 1 1918
De La Mer, Alice, Paulet Thevanaz, privately printed 1922
Dell, Floyd, The Angel Intrudes, Flying Stag Plays, No. 3, New York 1918
Playboy Nos. 1-9 1919-1924 and assorted fragments
The Quill, Vol. 2, No. 2 1918
A Pagan Anthology, New York: Pagan Publishing Company ca. 1918
Subject and Genre Headings
Industrial Design; Arens, Egmont, 1889-1966.; Kent, Rockwell, 1882-1971.; Stout, Rex, 1886-1975.; Columbian Rope Company.; Flying Stag Press.; Great Atlantic & Pacific Tea Company.; J.C. Penney Co.; Reynolds Metals Company.; Industrial design -- United States.; Industrial designers -- United States.; Art and industry.; Articles.; Blueprints (reprographic copies); Clippings (information artifacts); Correspondence.; Lantern slides.; Lectures.; News releases.; Photographs.; Sketches.; Exhibition catalogs.; Slides (photographs); Industrial designers.
Access Restrictions
The majority of our archival and manuscript collections are housed offsite and require advanced notice for retrieval. Researchers are encouraged to contact us in advance concerning the collection material they wish to access for their research.
Acquisition Information
Gift of Egmont Arens.
Inventory
- Personal correspondence
  - 1883 Nov - 1910 Jun (Box 1)
  - 1910 Jul - 1913 Aug (Box 2)
  - 1913 Sep - 1914 Dec (Box 3)
  - 1915 Jan - 1921 Dec (Box 4)
  - 1922 Jan - 1933 Dec (Box 5)
  - 1934 Jan - 1940 Dec (Box 6)
  - 1941 Jan - 1949 Dec (Box 7)
  - 1950 Jan - 1954 Dec (Box 8)
  - 1955 Jan - 1966 Feb (Box 9)
  - undated
    - A-C (Box 10)
    - Arens, Camille Davied, 7 folders (Box 10)
    - Arens, Emma Huegal, 3 folders (Box 11)
    - Arens, Josephine Bell (Box 11)
    - Arens, Ralph Waldo (Box 11)
    - Arens, Winifred B. (Box 11)
    - Baird, Bill (Box 11)
    - Cronyn, George (Box 11)
    - D-G (Box 11)
    - H (Box 11)
    - J-K (Box 12)
    - L-M (Box 12)
    - N-R (Box 12)
    - S-Z (Box 12)
    - Unidentified (Box 12)
- Industrial design records
  - Client and project file
    - Aerosleep Bed, undated; poster (Oversize 1)
    - Aerosol Can, 1963; sketches, correspondence (Box 13)
    - American Design Registration Institute, 1936; correspondence (Box 13)
    - American Tobacco Company, Lucky Strike Advertising Ideas, undated; p.r. mat., photo., handwritten note (Box 13)
    - Apron Fastener, undated; sketch (Box 13)
    - Art Exhibit, "Junk is My Hobby", 1941; correspondence, handwritten notes p.r. mat. (Box 13)
    - Ashtray, 1947; marketing survey (Box 13)
    - Avery Corporation, Paper Doll Project, 1951; correspondence, handwritten notes, pr. mat. (Box 13)
    - B & K Economy Stores, Ltd., undated; layout (Box 13)
    - Battery Case, 1938; patent application (Box 13)
    - Battleship, 1942; sketches, painting, cartoon, article (Box 13)
    - Better Finishes & Coatings, Inc., undated; photo, pr. mat (Box 13)
    - Billboard Projection, 1938 - 1939; sketches, handwritten notes, pr. mat., correspondence (Box 13)
    - Block & Guggenheimer, 1940; clippings (Box 13)
    - Book ideas
      - Biography of Frank Harris, 1929; 1932; correspondence, handwritten notes, clippings, (Box 13)
      - "Diagram for Tomorrow", 1938-1939; clippings, correspondence, (Einstein) (Box 13)
      - "Rackets", 1934-1936; clippings (Box 13)
      - Miscellaneous, 1929-1964; undated; clippings, handwritten notes, correspondence (Box 13)
    - Bottle, 1957; patent specification (Box 13)
    - Bottle Carrier, 1939-1940; photo., correspondence, photostats, patent copies, claim for invention (Box 13)
    - Bowl, undated; sketches (Box 13)
    - Box: all black, 1947-1949; sketch, correspondence (Box 13)
    - Briddell, Charles, Inc., undated; clipping (Box 13)
    - Brillo Manufacturing Company, 1949; 1950,; 1957; correspondence, notes, clipping (Box 13)
    - Bristol-Myers, 1958; pr. mat. (Box 13)
    - Bristol Laboratories, Inc., 1945; clipping (Box 13)
    - Cake Container, 1941; claim for invention (Box 13)
    - Caldwell, A. & G.J., Inc., 1934; pr. mat. (Box 13)
    - Calvert Lithographing Company, 1957; labels, evaluations by E.A., letter (Box 13)
    - Camera, 1930; report (Box 13)
    - Camouflage, 1942; correspondence, handwritten notes, mimeo. mat. (Box 13)
    - Carborundum Company, 1946; photo., pr. mat. (Box 13)
    - Center for Research in Package Marketing, 1957 - 1958; correspondence, report, news release (Box 13)
    - Chair (Beach), 1935; correspondence, sketch, patent copies (Box 13)
    - Chair (Plywood), 1939-1940; correspondence, sketches, renderings, handwritten notes, blueprint; 2 folders (Box 13)
    - Chairs, undated; sketches (Box 14)
    - Chaplin, Charlie, 1931-1938; animated film idea, correspondence, clippings (Box 14)
    - Chrysler Corporation, 1934; magazine idea, correspondence (Box 14)
    - Cigarette filters, (TNT), 1945-1960; correspondence, sketches, handwritten notes, photostats, certificate of trademark registration (Box 14)
    - Cigarette Packaging & Method of Making, 1931; patent petition, patent assignment, correspondence (Box 14)
    - Colgate-Palmolive Company, Bottle, 1960; correspondence, patent application (Box 14)
    - Colonial Sugar, Consumer Preference Survey by Container Corporation of America, undated; layout (Box 14)
    - Columbian Rope Company
      - Aluminum furniture
        - correspondence, handwritten notes, 1944-1945 (Box 14)
        - Photo, undated (Box 14)
        - Photostats, letter, 1944 (Box 14)
        - handwritten notes, rough sketches, 1945; undated (Box 14)
        - Photostats, sketches, 1945 (Box 14)
        - Photostats, 1945 (Box 14)
      - Co-Ro-Lite
        - Artek Pascoe furniture, 1944-1946; correspondence, sketches photostats, notices, photo. (Box 14)
        - Baby carriages, 1943-1945; correspondence, handwritten notes, sketches (Box 14)
        - Barrel, 1944-1947; correspondence, handwritten notes, sketches, photo. (Box 14)
        - Boat, 1934; correspondence, captions (Box 14)
        - Boat hulls, correspondence, handwritten notes, sketches, pr. mat., photostat, blue prints, 1943-1946; photo., photostats, 1944-1945; 2 folders (Box 14)
        - Book: Low Pressure Molding
          - handwritten, ts notes, 1944-1947 (Box 15)
          - correspondence, 1944-1947 (Box 15)
          - Draft, 1945 (Box 15)
          - Photo., pr. mat., 1943-1945 (Box 15)
        - Chair
          - correspondence, 1949-1950 (Box 15)
          - Clippings re: posture studies, undated (Box 15)
          - Clippings re: chair, 1949 (Box 15)
          - Miscellaneous, 1948; undated (Box 15)
          - Sketches, ca. 1944; undated (Box 15)
          - Sketches re: posture studies, undated (Box 15)
          - Photo., undated (Box 15)
        - Competition, 1944; correspondence, clippings (Box 15)
        - Co-Ro-Lite in combination with Jersey Cloth, 1943-1945; correspondence, handwritten notes (Box 15)
        - Debossed rubber molding blanket, 1944; correspondence, handwritten notes (Box 15)
        - Designs for uses, sketches, photostats, undated; 2 folders (Box 15)
        - Felt: Stretchable, 1944; undated; correspondence, sketches (Box 16)
        - Filaments, 1944-1945; 1955; correspondence, patent application, handwritten notes, pr. mat. (Box 16)
        - Furniture, 1943-1946; correspondence, sketches, pr. mat. (Box 16)
        - John Wesley Hyatt (Award for the Advertising of Plastics), 1945; correspondence, report, blueprint (Box 16)
        - Industrial Machine Housing, undated; sketch (Box 16)
        - Laboratory & Design Project, 1943-1945; correspondence, photo-stats, notes (Box 16)
        - Luggage, 1943-1944; sketches, handwritten notes, correspondence (Box 16)
        - Materials, 1943-1944; correspondence (Box 16)
        - Miscellaneous, undated; sketches (Box 16)
        - Patent Material, 1943-1945; correspondence, patent applications, assignment, handwritten notes (Box 16)
        - Publicity
          - correspondence, 1943-1946 (Box 16)
          - Copy, 1943-1945; undated (Box 16)
          - Pr. mat., 1940-1946 (Box 16)
        - Report of Progress, 1944-1945; report, correspondence, notes (Box 17)
    - Copyrights and Design Protection, 1935-1960; correspondence (Box 17)
    - Crystalace, undated; letter of agreement (Box 17)
    - Cubicles for Hotels, 1949; correspondence (Box 17)
    - Cups: Molded, undated; sketch (Box 17)
    - Derris, Inc., 1933; clipping (Box 17)
    - Dixon Pencil Company, 1941; sketches (Box 17)
    - Doll, Styrene, Electrostatic, 1950; affidavit (Box 17)
    - Drawer, undated; sketch (Box 17)
    - Electric Reel, undated; sketch (Box 17)
    - Elon Bede, 1945; trademark registration (Box 17)
    - Exhibit: Dayton, Ohio, undated; captions (Box 17)
    - Fastening & Tight Packaging
      - Means & methods of providing same, patent application, 1945-1948; sketches, photostats, correspondence, legal papers (Box 17)
    - Food Fair Stores, Inc., 1950-1958; labels and wrappers, handwritten notes (Box 17)
    - Fuller & Smith & Ross, Inc., 1949-1952; correspondence, sketch, handwritten notes (Box 17)
    - Furniture: Unibox, 1942; sketches, correspondence, handwritten notes (Box 17)
    - Gasoline Station, 1932; clipping, photo. (Box 17)
    - Glass Dress, 1939; clippings, photo. (Box 17)
    - Glue, 1941; correspondence, legal papers (Box 17)
    - Gobel, Alfred, Ind., undated; ham package label, sketches (Box 17)
    - Great Atlantic & Pacific Tea Company
      - Clippings, 1934-1955 (Box 17)
      - Bread products report, 1935 (Box 17)
      - Cereal packages report, 1952 (Box 17)
      - Eight O'Clock Coffee poster, mounted, undated (Map-case 131)
      - Sample label, sketches, 1940-1950; undated (Box 17)
    - Hat Display Stand, 1937; correspondence, photostat (Box 18)
    - Heide, Henry, Inc., 1960; undated; photo., clipping, (Box 18)
    - Heinz, H.J., Inc., 1941; labels, letter, sketches (Box 18)
    - Helmet, 1957-1959; correspondence, patent application (Box 18)
    - Higgins Ink Company, ca. 1938; clipping, layout, photo. (Box 18)
    - Hobart Brothers, Inc.
      - Electric Welder
        - correspondence, 1942-1945 (Box 18)
        - Photo., photostats, 1943; undated (Box 18)
        - Proposal, 1943 (Box 18)
        - Sketches, handwritten notes, 1943? (Box 18)
      - Kitchen Aid Line
        - Correspondence, 1941-1963 (Box 18)
        - Office design for E. A. Hobart, 1942-1944; correspondence, handwritten notes (Box 18)
        - Poster, mounted, undated (Map-case 131)
        - Publicity, clippings, 1934-1938; undated (Box 18)
        - Sketches, blueprints, handwritten notes, personnel brochure, layout, 1959-1963 (Box 18)
    - Hobart Manufacturing Company
      - Food mixing apparatus, 1939; patent oath, petition, assignment (photostats) (Box 18)
      - Model 100 Scale, 1941; correspondence, patent oath, petition, assignment, photostat (Box 18)
    - Holding Frame for Label or Direction for Application to Coffee Mill or the Like, 1934; patent application (Box 18)
    - Hollow-Wall Construction, 1935; sketches, correspondence, pr. mat. (Box 18)
    - Holsum Unified Bakeries, undated; label, publicity (Box 18)
    - Hotel of the Future, 1936-1940; correspondence, handwritten notes, proposal (Box 18)
    - Houseboat, 1933-1934; correspondence, handwritten notes (Box 18)
    - Household Tools, 1939-1940; sketches, claims for invention, correspondence (Box 18)
    - House of Sidney Johnson, 1948-1949; correspondence, sketches, pr. mat. (Box 18)
    - Housing: Prefabricated, 1932-1935; sketches, handwritten notes, correspondence, clippings (Box 19)
    - Hydraulic Engine, 1941-1942; correspondence, legal papers, sketches, blueprint, report (Box 19)
    - Ice Cube Ejector, 1941-1942; correspondence, sketch, blueprint, handwritten (Box 19)
    - Ice Cube Freezer, 1941; correspondence, sketches, blueprint (Box 19)
    - Industrial Equipment, undated; redesign notes (Box 19)
    - Industrial Tape Corporation, 1945-1954; correspondence, photo., layout, clipping (Box 19)
    - Industries Sales Committee, Home Caravan Project, 1934; correspondence, reports, sketches (Box 19)
    - Interstate Highway System, 1930-1937; correspondence, clippings (Box 19)
    - Jar Ring Device, 1935-1936; correspondence (Box 19)
    - Jigger Tubes, 1935; sketches, blueprint (Box 19)
    - Julian, Bernard, Inc., undated; clipping (Box 19)
    - Labels, correspondence, 1934; correspondence re: legal requirements, 1939, 1955 (Box 19)
    - Lampshade, 1937-1938; sketches, blueprint, correspondence (Box 19)
    - Lever Brothers Company, Lux Soap, undated; case history (Box 19)
    - Life Boat, Torpedo, 1942; sketch, photostat, letter (Box 19)
    - Life Magazine, 1932; 1937; correspondence, handwritten notes, (Box 19)
    - Sample layout, undated (Box 19)
    - Liquid Dispense, 1944; correspondence, sketch, handwritten, notes (Box 19)
    - Lumber System: Self-Membering Agreement, 1942; sketches (Box 19)
    - Magazine (unnamed), 1933; ideas, correspondence (Box 19)
    - Manhattan Inner Loop Skyway, (Skyloop)
      - correspondence, 1945-1947 (Box 19)
      - Clippings, notes, 1948-1950; undated (Box 20)
      - Maps, photo. ca., 1946 (Box 20)
      - Manhattan Skyloop Committee
        - Correspondence, notes, 1946 (Box 20)
        - Legal form, ca. 1946 (Box 20)
        - Literature, ca. 1946 (Box 20)
        - Rendering, ca. 1946 (Oversize 1)
      - Townway Plan
        - correspondence, 1953-1961 (Box 20)
        - Miscellaneous, 1951-1953 (Box 20)
        - Photographs, photostats, undated (Box 20)
        - Presentations, 1945-1953; 2 folders (Box 20)
        - Rough drafts, ca. 1953 (Box 20)
    - Mars, Inc. correspondence, 1955 (Box 20)
    - Memo valet, correspondence, 1937 (Box 20)
    - Merkin, M.J. Paint Company, Inc., 1950; correspondence (Box 20)
    - Motor Boat, 1929-1931; correspondence, handwritten notes, clippings (Box 20)
    - Multiple Projection, 1939; correspondence (Box 20)
    - Mutual Life Insurance Company, undated; layout (Box 20)
    - Nashua Corporation, 1963; label dispenser, correspondence, handwritten notes, specifications (Box 20)
    - Nashua Package Sealing Company, 1941; tape dispenser, patent oath, specification, petition, correspondence (Box 20)
    - National Biscuit Company, Packaging program, 1947; report & recommendations (Box 20)
    - National Biscuit Company, Repackaging program, 1940; report & recommendations (Box 21)
    - Nestle Company, Inc., undated (Box 21)
    - Nestle-Lemur Company, Hairdryer, 1939; patent application, (photostat) clippings (Box 21)
    - New York Herald Tribune, Rotogravure layouts, 1935; correspondence, handwritten notes (Box 21)
    - New York Zoological Society, Conservation exhibit, 1950; letter, proposal (Box 21)
    - North Bros., undated; clipping (Box 21)
    - Nowland & Company, Inc., 1960; correspondence (Box 21)
    - Oil Can Opener, 1933; claim for invention, handwritten notes, correspondence (Box 21)
    - Oleomargarine Color Mixer, correspondence, 1945-1946; handwritten notes (Box 21)
    - Paris & Peart, 1938; consent & release (Box 21)
    - Paper Bag Closure (Seal Tack), 1943; correspondence, sketch (Box 21)
    - Panel Fastener, 1955; correspondence, patent, photostats (Box 21)
    - Panglo Lamps, 1931-1932; correspondence, sketches, photo., pr. mat. (Box 21)